# **Dominic Bordelon**

412-585-3755 | dominic.bordelon@gmail.com

# Summary

Adaptable research support specialist and information professional in an R1 university library setting, now transitioning toward a data science career via a graduate certificate in Applied Data-Driven Methods. International experience with a talent for engaging with varied domain experts. Unifies skills in data management and analysis, cultural competence, academic research, and technical communication with diverse stakeholders and clients.

### **Skills**

**Computer programming and communication:** R, Python, SQL, data modeling, data validation, HTML, CSS, HTTP, Git, technical writing

**Analytics:** cleaning/munging, data integration, basic statistical modeling, data visualization, web APIs **Interpersonal:** information needs analysis, cultural competency, ethnographic interviewing **Languages:** English, Spanish, German

# Experience

Research Data Librarian, University of Pittsburgh – Pittsburgh, PA

Nov 2019 – present

- Consults with faculty, post-doctoral fellows, and student researchers in a variety of disciplines about data management, computer programming, and research methods to help them solve problems in pursuit of their research (60 consultations in 2022)
- Develops and leads introductory workshops for data science skills for the university community, mitigating computational-method gaps that exist in formal curricula (107 trainees in 2022)
- Created and hosts a weekly R and RStudio Drop-In Hour for the university community, enabling students to get free technical tutoring for assignments and projects (24 attendees in 2022)
- Delivers talks for faculty about data management, data sharing, reproducibility, and data privacy to better inform their research proposals to major funders and their responsible research practices (79 attendees in 2022)
- Collaborates with faculty in delivering course instruction to students, presenting guest lectures and supporting group projects with mentorship, to enhance learning with additional perspectives and expertise

Library Technology Specialist, European Southern Observatory–Garching, Germany Oct 2015–Oct 2019

- Developed software and databases (LAMP stack) for tracking publications that used observatory data (~4,200 articles for 2016-19) as a research tool for astronomers and an impact tool for data-informed decision-making by observatory administrators
- Implemented an intranet service (HTTP REST API) with internet landing pages for observatory departments to register digital object identifiers (DOIs), resulting in citable persistent identifiers for observatory publications and data sets
- Designed and built a variety of dashboards and tools for managing resources of the Office for Science, greatly facilitating logistics for students, fellows, and visiting scholars

• Fulfilled information requests in a specialized and international setting, connecting astronomers and engineers with needed information for research and development

Computer Services Librarian, E. Baton Rouge Parish Library – Baton Rouge, LA May 2014 – Sept 2015

- Conceived and implemented makerspace programming using Arduino DIY electronics kits for the general public, guiding participants in engagement with technology and computer programming
- Transferred and automated existing record-keeping workflows to save many staff-hours for statistical reporting and to provide a robust database solution for financial data (MS SQL Server)
- Solved IT support cases, including within the library management system, to correct errors and increase patron satisfaction

Reference Librarian, E. Baton Rouge Parish Library – Baton Rouge, LA

Tutor (Part-time), Academic Ctr. for Student-Athletes, LSU – Baton Rouge, LA

Library Technician, E. Baton Rouge Parish Library – Baton Rouge, LA

Teaching Assistant, Dept. of English, LSU – Baton Rouge, LA

Spanish Teacher, Port Allen High School – Port Allen, LA

June 2013 – May 2015

August 2012 – May 2015

August 2009 – May 2010

August 2008 – May 2009

## Education

Graduate Certificate in Applied Data-Driven Methods – University of Pittsburgh	Expected Fall 2024
Master of Library and Information Science – Louisiana State University	2013
Bachelor of Arts, Spanish – Louisiana State University	2008
Bachelor of Arts, History – Louisiana State University	2008
Bachelor of Arts, English, concentration: Writing & Culture – Louisiana State University	ity 2007

#### **Carpentries Certified Instructor** – The Carpentries

2020

#### Selected Publications

- Phillips, G. A., Bordelon, D., & Kapral, T. T. (2023). <u>"Push That Button and See What Happens": Addressing Technology Anxiety in Library Digital Scholarship Pedagogy.</u> In *Digital Humanities Workshops*. Routledge.
- Bordelon, D. (2022, October 6). *Documentation literacy as a metacognitive skill in computer programming*. Midwest Data Librarian Symposium, Notre Dame University.
- Bordelon, Dominic. (2022). The New College Try: Enrolling in First-Year Science Courses as Embedded Librarianship. <a href="https://doi.org/10.17605/OSF.IO/NUEX5">https://doi.org/10.17605/OSF.IO/NUEX5</a>
- Kerzendorf, W. E., Patat, F., Bordelon, D., van de Ven, G., & Pritchard, T. A. (2020). Distributed peer review enhanced with natural language processing and machine learning. *Nature Astronomy*. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41550-020-1038-y">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41550-020-1038-y</a>
- Bordelon, D., Grothkopf, U., & Meakins, S. (2018). First Light for DOIs at ESO. *EPJ Web of Conferences,* 186, 04003. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1051/epiconf/201818604003">https://doi.org/10.1051/epiconf/201818604003</a>
- Patat, F., Boffin, H. M. J., Bordelon, D., Grothkopf, U., Meakins, S., Mieske, S., & Rejkuba, M. (2017). The ESO Survey of Non-Publishing Programmes. *The Messenger, 170*, 51–57. https://doi.org/10.18727/0722-6691/5055
- Leibundgut, B., Bordelon, D., Grothkopf, U., & Patat, F. (2017). Scientific Return from VLT instruments. *The Messenger, 169*, 11–15. https://doi.org/10.18727/0722-6691/5032